{"tossups": [{"question": "In this war, forces under Johann von Werth were entrenched near Allerheim at a battle where Franz von Marcy was killed. The Truce of Ulm forced Maximilian I of Bavaria to break his alliance with Ferdinand III during this war. At the Battle of Zusmarshausen, the last battle of this war, a combined Franco-Swedish army completely destroyed the Holy Roman Empire\u2019s forces. Gustavus Adolphus died at the Battle of Lutzen during, for the point, what war that ended with the 1648 Peace of Westphalia?", "answer": "<b> Thirty Years\u2019</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man wrote a<em> Book of Squares</em> that was devoted to analyzing second degree Diophantine equations and dedicated to his friend, Holy Roman Emperor Frederick II. This man pioneered the use of the horizontal bar in modern fraction notation, and his book<em> Liber Abaci</em> popularized the Arabic numeral system in the Western world. The golden ratio is approximated by successive ratios in a pattern studied by this man. For the point, name this Italian mathematician who lends his name to a sequence beginning 1, 1, 2, 3, 5.", "answer": "<b> Fibonacci</b> (accept<b> Leonardo of Pisa</b>; prompt on Leonardo)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {"question": "Economist Henry George was an advocate for an \u201ceconomy wide\u201d tax on this resource. In<em> The</em> <em>Tragedy of the Commons</em>, Garret Hardin argued that government intervention and privatization were needed to manage this resource, which the Physiocrats claimed was the sole source of wealth in society. Labor, capital, and this resource are the primary factors of production. For the point, name this economic resource, large plots of which are used in agriculture.", "answer": "<b> land</b> (prompt on property)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {}, {"question": "French painter Rosa Bonheur turns away from Napoleon to paint this man in an 1896 advertisement showing Bonheur\u2019s depiction of this man on horseback. This entrepreneur advertised \u201cReal Sons of the Soudan\u201d and \u201cGenuine Cuban Insurgents\u201d as opponents for staged battles in performances of his\u201cCongress of Rough Riders of the World,\u201d which included Sitting Bull and Annie Oakley. For the point, name this American soldier and showman who organized a namesake Wild West Show.", "answer": "<b> Buffalo Bill</b> (accept Colonel William Frederick<b> Cody</b>; prompt on \u201cBill\u201d)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A pig farmer from this country led a rebellion against the Mongols and was named Ivaylo the Radish. A writer from this country, Georgi Markov, was assassinated via a ricin pellet fired from an umbrella. Bashi-bazouk forces massacred this country\u2019s civilians in the April Uprising, leading William Gladstone to denounce this country\u2019s \u201cHorrors.\u201d This country gained autonomy from the Ottoman Empire in the Treaty of San Stefano. Todor Zhivkov once led, for the point, what Balkan country governed from Sofia?", "answer": "<b> Bulgaria</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A series of publications by James Callender prompted this man to expose a blackmail scheme involving over $1,300 paid by this man to John Reynolds in order to keep an affair with his wife Maria secret. This man, Thomas Jefferson, and James Madison orchestrated the Compromise of 1790, in which state debts were assumed by the federal government and the capital was moved south; the assumption was key to this Cabinet member\u2019s plan for reforming the US economy. For the point, name this first US Secretary of the Treasury.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Hamilton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Despite facing a numerically greater force, this man\u2019s forces emerged victorious at the Battle of Pun\u00b4a against natives and at the Battle of Las Salinas against Diego de Almagro. After the Battle of Cajamarca, this man took a leader hostage when that leader threw a Bible to the ground. This explorer later collected rooms full of gold and silver as ransom, but killed that leader, Atahualpa, anyway. For the point, name this Spanish conquistador who conquered the Inca Empire.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Pizarro</b> Gonz\u00b4alez", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Before this event, administrator Thomas Paine met with Ralph Abernathy, whose group protested this event as a \u201cmisplaced priority\u201d of the government. William Safire wrote a conditional speech in case of disaster during this event; that speech was not delivered by Richard Nixon. This event, which attained a national goal set in 1961, featured Michael Collins manning the command module<em> Columbia</em> while the <em>Eagle</em> landed at Tranquility Base. For the point, name this NASA mission in which Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong landed on the Moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo 11</b> landing (accept answers related to the<b> first Moon landing</b> until \u201cMoon\u201d is read, and prompt after; prompt on just \u201cmoon landing\u201d; prompt on \u201cApollo (missions)\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A series of reforms named for this dynasty reformed courts called Royal Audiences to give more power to<em> peninsulares</em>. This dynasty came to power after the eventual death of a ruler who \u201cbaffled Christendom by continuing to live,\u201d Charles II. The ascension of this dynasty led to a war in which the Duke of Marlborough won the Battle of Blenheim [BLEN-em]. This dynasty gained power in one country after the Treaty of Utrecht confirmed the ascension of Philip V. For the point, name this dynasty that ruled Spain after the Hapsburgs.", "answer": "House of<b> Bourbon</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Early in his career, this man successfully defended his country from Isidro Barradas and earned the nickname \u201cHero of Tampico.\u201d This man, who came to power after signing the Plan of Casa Mata in 1822 to overthrow Agustin Iturbide [ee-TOOR-bee-day], lost his leg during the Pastry War against France. Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie were killed in fighting against the forces of, for the point, what Mexican leader who was victorious at the Alamo?", "answer": "Antonio Lopez de<b> Santa Anna</b> (or Antonio de Padua Maria Severino L\u00b4opez de Santa Anna y P\u00b4erez de Lebr\u00b4on)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first printing press in Britain\u2019s North American colonies was installed at this school. After emigrating to the US, Louis Agassiz became a geology professor at this university, whose presidents have included Increase Mather. This university\u2019s undergraduates live in houses named for the Lowell family, the Adams family, and John Winthrop. Radcliffe College was the sister school of, for the point, what Ivy League university along the Charles River in Cambridge, Massachusetts?", "answer": "<b> Harvard</b> College (accept<b> Harvard</b> University)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This province, the western part of the proposed Buffalo province, grew via oil and gas revenue after the Athabasca Oil Sands were harvested in the 20th century. Its economy was once dominated by farming and ranching, a heritage reflected in an annual \u201cStampede\u201d held in its capital. For the point, name this Canadian province, between British Columbia and Saskatchewan, where Fort Calgary was built.", "answer": "<b> Alberta</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Traders in this state developed a pidgin language called Haida Jargon to speak with Europeans. This state\u2019s proposed Gravina Island Bridge to Ketchikan gained the nickname \u201cBridge to Nowhere\u201d by critics of Senator Ted Stevens. This state\u2019s agricultural Kenai Peninsula is bordered by an arm of the Cook Inlet. The Stampede Trail is in a park in this state whose name means \u201cThe High One\u201d in Athabaskan. A historic dog race ends at the city of Nome in, for the point, what state that contains Denali and the city of Anchorage?", "answer": "<b> Alaska</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man besieged a \u201cStraw City\u201d at Alessandria while trying to depose Pope Alexander III, and failed to negotiate peace at Montebello. Four Bolognese jurists ruled that this man had divine right in the Diet of Roncaglia. This emperor supported antipope Victor IV and feuded with the Lombard League. This emperor diverted some of Saladin\u2019s forces from the Battle of Acre after joining a coalition with Philip Augustus and Richard the Lionheart. For the point, name this Holy Roman Emperor who drowned in the Third Crusade and was nicknamed for his red beard.", "answer": "<b> Frederick I</b> Holy Roman Emperor (or<b> Frederick Barbarossa</b>; prompt on Frederick alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This case\u2019s ruling prompted Virginia governor Thomas Stanley to create the Gray Commission. The massive resistance movement began in response to this ruling, which was influenced by a series of doll tests carried out by Kenneth and Mamie Clark. This case\u2019s ruling, which was to be implemented with\u201call deliberate speed,\u201d overturned the doctrine of \u201cseparate from equal\u201d from<em> Plessy v. Ferguson</em>. For the point, name this 1954 Supreme Court case that ruled that segregated public schools were unconstitutional.", "answer": "<b> Brown</b> v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In an attempt to justify this event, operatives led by Alfred Naujocks took over a radio station and sent an inflammatory message during the Gleiwitz Incident. \u201cCase White\u201d was the plan for this event, which called for an assault from three directions, including from East Prussia. The Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact secured Soviet involvement in this event, which began on September 1, 1939. For the point, name this act of German aggression that triggered World War II and resulted in the capture of Warsaw.", "answer": "Nazi Germany\u2019s<b> invasion of Poland</b> (prompt on descriptions of the start of World War II before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s comment that one should check their complacency as often as washing their face is quoted in a chapter called \u201cCriticism and Self-Criticism.\u201d This man succeeded Otto Braun after a disagreement in strategy at the Zunyi Conference. This leader, who used the Battle of Luding Bridge as propaganda, took power in a campaign that included the Long March and attempted to purge Western ideals through the Cultural Revolution. For the point, name this founder of the communist People\u2019s Republic of China.", "answer": "<b> Mao</b> Zedong (or<b> Mao</b> Tse-tung)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 212 BC, an annual festival to this deity gave the Romans under Marcus Claudius Marcellus an opportunity to capture Syracuse in which Archimedes was killed. A queen named after this goddess sank her own ships to escape from the Battle of Salamis. A marble temple dedicated to this goddess was located in Ephesus and listed among the Seven Wonders of the World. Agamemnon sacrificed his daughter, Iphigenia, during the Trojan War to appease, for the point, what Greek goddess of hunting, the twin sister of Apollo?", "answer": "<b> Artemis</b> (accept<b> Diana</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In January 2018, Emmanuel Macron announced that this object will leave France for the first time in 950 years, going on public display at the British Museum in London. Queen Matilda and Bishop Odo are the people primarily believed to have commissioned this work, which includes a probable depiction of Halley\u2019s Comet. This work, whose surviving portion is 225 feet long and 1.5 feet high, is technically an embroidery. The Battle of Hastings is depicted in, for the point, what 11th century \u201ctapestry?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Bayeux</b> Tapestry", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this European ethnicity was Argentine president Edelmiro Julian Farrell, who enabled Juan Peron\u2019s rise to power. Another member of this ethnicity was Paraguayan First Lady Eliza Lynch, the wife of Paraguayan dictator Francisco Solano Lopez. Another member of this ethnicity ruled Chile from 1817 to 1823 after the Chilean War of Independence; that man was Bernardo O\u2019Higgins. For the point, name this European ethnicity whose members fought in the Mexican-American War in St. Patrick\u2019s Battalion.", "answer": "<b> Irish</b> people (accept people from<b> Ireland</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}